Hi, we will be talking about curves and splines.
Basically, because when we are working with animations,
they will have often the time when you will want to encode your animation.
And somehow, if you have keyframes, you want to be able to have
an interpretation between those keyframes. Or you might
have an object that has to follow a certain path.
So, mathematically, we will be using curves.
types of curves and so I wanted to have those videos to show you the mathematical background
behind a few of them so when we'll be doing white papers I will be able to just copy the
code from this notebook and reuse them inside of our studies. When we talk about curve and spline
basically we have two types of curves we have the approximation curves and we have the interpolation
curves. Interpolation curves is the one you will want to use when you encode your animation data
as keyframes. You will want to make sure that actually your interpolation goes through all
the keyframes you set, and then you have in-betweens computed for you. That's the interpolation
curves. In that case, we will study the helmet curves, and we will have the cardinal spline as
And you have the approximation curves, which is the fact that you don't need your curve
to go through every points, but you need to follow the data points as close as possible.
And on the approximation curve, we will be using the Bezier curve, which is the most
known one. And as it extends, we will be studying the cubic
B's plane. So as a first one, we will be studying the basic
curve. And what the basic curve is, is the most known one. In
the industry, when we talk about animations, usually is the
basic curve you encounter the first time. And we will be
studying the basic curve through the Castell-Geo algorithm and first before going in through the
mathematics and all that kind of stuff, what I would do is I will actually show you what it is
and how it works and then we could see what is the mathematical formula for it. So a basic curve
can be computed with any number of points. The only important part is that to know that the
the basic curve is parametrized by a t-value usually that goes between 0 and 1 and the
idea is that at time 0 you are at your the position of your first point and at t1 you
will be at the position of your last point. So if I draw the basic curve for the simple
case of a quadratic one. What you have is the we start at the first point, we end at the last
point and we have the curve that goes towards the the point in between. And how the Castel
Joaquin compute this it's basically by a bunch of linear interpolation. So what you do is that
you take the linear interpolation of the point one and two that give you that yellow one and you
you do the same with point 2 and 3 and I'll give you that red one and now that you have those two
points you again do the linear interpolation between those two points and that give you
the point on the Bezier curve and between zero and one it draws the entire Bezier curve this way
and it works with any degrees so in this case I've showed you with the quadratic one if I go
cubic so with the four points it is the same concept except that you have more steps of course
you do interpolation between the first and second the second and third the third and fourth
and so on and so on and you repeat every time and it works for any number of points as I said
and the mathematical formula for it is a recursive function basically says that
that a Bezier curve that has only one point
is equal to that point, that's it.
And any other Bezier curve that is defined with,
in this case, N point is just equal
to the linear interpolation with the Bezier curve
that goes from point zero to point N minus one
and the Bezier curve that goes from point one to point N.
So it's really a simple algorithm.
It's really stable mathematically.
So it's the one that's usually used
and presented the first time.
And you can see that's the actual entire algorithm.
Everything else is just to draw the graph here.
So take a list of points.
If there is only one point, you return it.
And if there is more than one,
you'd call back that function with the two different ranges and you do the linear interpolation
between them. That's it, that's the Castelgio algorithm. Now, the Castelgio algorithm is
well known and easy to use, but there is another way to compute a Bezier curve that you will
probably uncontrollable at some point and it's to go through the Bernstein polynomials.
So what are the Bernstein polynomials? It's a way of computing a bunch of functions depending
of the degrees you want to use. So a Bernstein polynomial of degree n is defined at this function
and basically is depending of the number on the the degree and the index and it's
also a function of t that goes between zero and one and as you can see k goes
from zero to n so if you do a bunch and polynomial of degree three you will have
four different base basically so let me show you what they are exactly so that's
the Bernstein basis just using that formula the binomial coefficients you
have here in front that brackets I'm using the comb functions from sci-pi and
And then if I just draw all of those,
so for instance, for a degree three,
I will go with degree one first.
You can see what happened.
A degree one, Bernstein will actually give you
two polynomial, you know,
and then you will have the first one
that starts at zero and value of one
and end at value zero at one,
and the second one is just the opposite.
And you could do as many of those and you could see that the first one already start at one and the last one always
End at one and in between you have those curves
the particularity of the Bernstein basis is that
At any point between zero and one if you sum all of your basis
You actually have one so you see the last one is the sum of my four
for my five different curves and
and it's equal to one. What the button bases are used usually for is for
approximation, basically without going too much in detail, because between zero
and one you can see you get a bunch of curves, so you could decide that you
could try to give a multiplier for all of those different curves to try to
to mimic any functions you receive as an input.
So what I have here is my green one
is the functions I tried to approximate
using the Bernstein basis.
And what I would do is that if I have degree one,
the best fit I can have is something is just a line.
But as soon as I start to get a bit more degrees,
I can actually get closer and closer
to the actual function I'm trying to approximate.
And now with a degree 13,
meaning with 14 coefficients,
I can approximate my curves the best as I can.
Now, that's usually where you will uncount the bone stain,
but in our case, it can also be used
to compute the Bezier curve.
and how you compute a Bayesian curve
thanks to the Bernstein polynomials.
You basically take all the Bernstein functions
for the degrees of the Bayesian curve you want to use.
So if I want to do a cubic Bayesian curve,
I will have four points,
meaning that I will have four different bases
for the Bernstein.
And I would just multiply my first point
with my first base, my second point,
second base, third point, my third base, 4.4 base and sum all of them and it will give me the
Bezier curve. So let me write my Bezier function this way. So I take the degrees and then I take
my burst and Bezes, multiply it by the points, do it for each points and sum the results. So that's
That's my function and you can see that if I just execute this function I will have the
same curves as the one I had before.
So it's my three points that my curves, four points curves and so on.
And it's equal to the shape I have here.
So that's the other way of computing the Bezier curve.
And to show you that we are actually computing exactly the same things, what I would do is
that I will use SimPy, which is the symbolic Mathematics library inside of Python.
And SimPy allow you to do math as in calculus, so you don't actually compute values.
You could use letters and keep those letters.
So what I would do is write the formula for a cubic Bezier using the Casteljeu algorithm.
So I do the linear interpolation for the first point, and so on, so on, and so forth, and
then I interpolate those two, those three, and then interpolate the final two.
I expand all the mathematics, and I try to rearrange them in a certain order to have
of P1, P2 and P3 explicitly defined in my function.
Now, I would do the same using the Bernstein formula,
so using the binomial and then the exponent
and the factors and multiply by the points.
So that's the entire Bernstein base,
multiply by the points and sum all those four.
And again, I expand and I try to refactorize
and collect the different values.
And if I do this, what I can see is that, of course,
it makes sense, you actually end up
with the exact same formula, which
is really proving that we were computing the same thing,
just using different means to reach them.
What I would do here quickly, but it
will be useful for later.
Don't worry, it doesn't make any sense at this point.
is to say that if what we want to do most of the time
is a cubic Bayesian, it also means
that I don't need to use the Bernstein formula
or I don't need to use the Castelgeo algorithm
because it's a cubic one and I've just computed exactly
what are the terms of that cubic.
It's always, it will always be those same values.
I don't need to go through the entire algorithm
to do linear interpolation and all that kind of stuff.
I could just use that formula and plug my P1, P2, P3, P4, meaning that I can actually turn this
into a matrix form and I will be useful because often at later stage we will be using matrix form
for a lot of different splines and different computations so at least let's get used to this
writing with the Bezier at this point. So what I do is I define a matrix and I
just reused the terms that I have for all of my points here. So the point
1 is minus t cubed 3t squared minus 3t plus 1. So I do my minus 1, 3, minus 3, 1
in the first column, 0.2 is 3 3 3 t cube minus 6 t square and so on and so on.
So I'll write them in column and now that I have that matrix I can have the
matrix for all the t's t cube t square t and 1 and I can also have the one for p1
p2 p3 p4 and basically what you do is that you write this as a matrix form
And just to prove to you that this is exactly the same computation at this one, but written
as a matrix, I could just execute the computation and you could see that you end up with the
exact same formula, right? One side note we could do about basic curve is what we call
the rational basic curve. I don't have any example here because it's more just to know
that it exists. Say if I need the mathematical formula at some point, I can grab and pick
it from here. But basically what rational basic curve is, is the fact that you could
say that you want to give more importance to a certain point that to another one. Say
you could say in the cubic one, the second point has two times more importance than the
third one and so you can give weights to each point to make the curves get closer to that point
relative to another one. So the formula is basically the same as the normal one.
You take your points and multiply with the Bernstein basis except that you also multiply it
by the weights. So each point has a weight and a Bernstein base and then you divide everything by
the sum of all the weights multiplied by the bandstand. So it's just to renormalize all
the weights to make sure that everything keeps a curve that goes between 0 and 1.
So you need to divide by the sum of all the weights you injected here.
And that's it, that's the formula. So basically it's the same as before except that you multiply
by the weights and then you re-divide by all the weights and you have the original Bezier curve.
And now that we have one Bayesian curve, usually what we want to do is to actually make a spline
with it, having several curves back-to-back so you could define a real shape and keep going and
keep working exactly as you do with keyframes. So what we will do is just having the system
to compute the Bezier you could see that at this time I know that I will be
using cubic Bezier so I've used the matrix notation to compute the Bezier
curve so I just do the matrix the multiply the point by the matrix and
then the times and that's it so and then when I want to compute the Bezier's
plan I would just take the first four points and do one base here with them
and then take the the next four points and do the base here with them and just
reusing the first and last base here the points so we can align them so
basically what you end up with is this so you'll have two base here of back to
back so that was my first second third and four and then my first second third and four points
and I'm sharing the points here in the three zeros for both Bezier. Now you've seen that what I've
done is I make the function for cubic Bezier and I said this will probably be the one we'll be using
most of the time is cubic and to be honest everything else in this mathematical introduction
will be about cubic spline, cubic anything, but it will be cubic every time. And so why
do we focus so much on the cubic? It's because if we were doing only linear interpolation between
all the points we have in our data, of course, the first thing we could do is line to a graph,
and that's not exactly how you would want to interpolate your animation, right?
If I go one degree higher and I go quadratic, what it means is the quadratic curve can actually
bend in one direction all the time and has to only bend in that one. So five of those four points
now I can have a nice curve that start at my first point reach the second and then keep going from
there with the same curvatures and go down but then here I'm blocked because either I would have to
go back up this direction and break my curve here or having a curvature in the opposite
direction and anyway I have a discontinuity here. So quadratic is not enough in our case here
and what we need to do is to go at least cubic because cubic allows you to have two curves
into your interpolations. So you can start with the one curvature and end with the opposite one
and you can see that as soon as you go cubic now I can have full continuity between all my lines
because I can curve up and then curve down curve down and curve up curve up and curve down so now
I'm able to interpolate my points and I don't need to go in a higher degrees because the cubic
is enough to actually curve both directions and that's it. I won't go further in the number of
degrees and that covers the cubic and the next time we will be going through a mid-curve and see
see why we do them.